<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lamentacion (by one of Englands prophets) over the ruines of this oppressed nacion, to be deeply layd to heart by Parliament and Army, and all sorts of peeple, lest they be swept away with the besom of destruction, in the day of the Lords fierce wrath and indignation, which is near at hand. Written by the movings of the Lord in James Nayler. And a vvarning to the rulers of England not to usurp dominion over the conscience, nor to give forth lawes contrary to that in the conscience. Written from the spirit of the Lord in George Fox.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E727_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202148</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862543</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862543</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E727[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lamentacion (by one of Englands prophets) over the ruines of this oppressed nacion, to be deeply layd to heart by Parliament and Army, and all sorts of peeple, lest they be swept away with the besom of destruction, in the day of the Lords fierce wrath and indignation, which is near at hand. Written by the movings of the Lord in James Nayler. And a vvarning to the rulers of England not to usurp dominion over the conscience, nor to give forth lawes contrary to that in the conscience. Written from the spirit of the Lord in George Fox.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho: Wayt at his house in the Pavement in York,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[York] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 27".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Quaker authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LAMENTACION (By one of <hi>Englands</hi> Prophets) Over the Ruines OF this oppreſſed Nacion, To be deeply layd to heart by <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> and all ſorts of Peeple, leſt they be ſwept away with the Beſom of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, in the Day of the Lords fierce wrath and Indignation, which is near at hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by the movings of the Lord in</hi> James Nayler.</p>
            <p>AND A WARNING TO the Rulers of England Not to uſurp Dominion over the Conſcience, nor to give forth Lawes contrary to that in the Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written from the Spirit of the Lord in</hi> George Fox.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Tho: Wayt</hi> at his houſe in the <hi>Pavement</hi> in <hi>York.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="lamentation">
            <pb facs="tcp:166821:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166821:2"/>
            <head>A LAMENTACION By one of <hi>Englands</hi> Prophets, over the Ruines of this oppreſſed NACION, to be deeply layd to heart by Parliament and Army, and all ſorts of People, leſt they be ſwept away with the Beſom of Deſtruction, in the day of the Lords fierce wrath and indignation, which is near at hand.</head>
            <p>OH <hi>England!</hi> how is thy expectation failed now after all thy travails? the People to whom Oppreſſion and Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs hath been a Burden, have long waited for Deliverance, from one year to another, but none comes, from one ſort of men to another.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou looked for Reformation, but all in vain! for as power hath come into the hands of men, it hath been turned into violence, and the will of men is brought forth inſtead of Equity, and this they ſeek to eſtabliſh by a Law, to which all muſt bow that are under them, or they muſt be judged as Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, ſo that which ſhould be for Deliverance of the ſimple from the hand of the oppreſſour, is turned into a ſnare to entrap the righteous, and he that turns from iniquity is made a prey to the wicked, and none lays it to heart through the Nation, for all hearts are full of oppreſſion, and all hands are full of violence, their houſes are filled with oppreſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their Streets and Markets abound with it, their Courts which ſhould afford remedy againſt it, are wholly made up of iniquity and injuſtice, and the Law of God is made altogether void<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and truth is troden under foot, and plainneſs is become odious to the proud, and Deceit ſet on high,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166821:3"/>
and the proud are counted happy, and the rich are exalted above the poore, and look to be worſhiped as God, which if any refuſe a ſnare is layd, and Bonds and Impriſonment is appointed for them, as not worthy to breathe in the ayer, and no Law, Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor Iuſtice can be heard for their freedom: and this is not done by an open Enemy, for then it had not bin ſo ſtrange unto thee, but it is done by thoſe who pretend to be againſt oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and for whom under that pretence thou haſt adventured all that is dear unto thee, to put power into their hands; and now thou cryeſt to them for help, but findeſt nøne that can deliver thee; Oh fooliſh People, when will ye learn wiſdom? when will ye ceaſe from man, who is vanity, and the ſons of men who are become a Ly?</p>
            <p>Are not theſe the choiceſt of thy Worthies, who are now in power? Hath it not been the top of thy deſires and labors to ſee it in their hands? and are not they now becom weak as other men, and the Land ſtill in travel, but nothing brought forth but winde? How is the wiſdom of the wiſe turned into folly, and the underſtanding of the prudent hid! How is he who ſeemed valiant for general freedom fallen into a particular earthly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and hath no power to help himſelf! Would any have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that theſe ſhould have fallen in the Pit, and ſtuck in the Mire, as they who were before them, whoſe names are made a reproach in the Nation! how have theſe cryed out for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to bear rule in his Church, and conſciences of his own, above the wils of proud oppreſſing Tyrants, yea and have been Inſtruments to execute Gods decree upon ſuch as have withſtood the freedom of the righteous ſeed; but now what is brought forth by them more than words! do not the members of <hi>Chriſtly</hi> ſtill under the power of the oppreſſor, caſt into holes and Priſons for the Truths ſake, and are denyed that liberty they allow to thieves and murderers, though the breach of no juſt Law can be layd to their charge, neither will they let them come to tryall, left by their own Law they ſhould be forced to free them; and how long ſome have layn upon this account you are not ignorant.</p>
            <p>Wo is me for you Rulers, how are you fallen from what you have profeſſed, when you your ſelves were ſufferers under ſuch
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166821:3"/>
bondage! and now is it nothing to you that your Brethren who have been one with you againſt oppreſſion, now periſh under the hand of the ſame men, from whom you are ſet free! and do not the ſame men judg us now for offenders, and doth it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern you to ſee what is the cauſe why they thus vent their envy againſt the innocent, and their Lives and Libertyes are taken away in cloſe holes and dungeons, when it is your duty and in your power to ſee them have juſtice, according to the Law of God which you profeſs, and not after mens wils: and if you know the offences for which they thus ſuffer, how is it that that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth command and the Saints did practice is now become ſo heynous offences that nothing will ſerve but perpetual Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment in cloſe holes without hearing or tryal! and that you may ſee for what theſe deſpiſed ones do ſuffer under you, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their crimes, whereof the greateſt of them is, that ſome of them are moved to go into the Idols Temples, to diſpute and reaſon with them who uphold the Idols worſhip, and to call the People out of it, unto the worſhip in Spirit; and though this ſeem a heinous crime to you, yet it was the practice of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Saints as is plain in Scripture.</p>
            <p>Others ſuffer becauſe they cannot break the expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, to give that worſhip to proud men, which God Almighty hath forbidden to give to any Creature in Heaven or in Earth, but onely to himſelf; and here may all the heathen Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers condemn you, who never impriſoned nor fined <hi>Chriſt</hi> nor his Saints for this, though the Scripture ſayth, they <hi>respected no mans perſon,</hi> nor did they <hi>bow down</hi> nor give <hi>worſhip</hi> to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though the Devil the father of pride tempted to it then as well as now.</p>
            <p>Others ſuffer for confeſſing the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him in them in their meaſure, as they finde him manifeſt in them to overcome ſin, the world, and the Devil, and reconcile them to God, and this is called Blaſphemy, and ſo proceeded againſt, though the Saints have always witneſſed the ſame, and it ſtands in Scripture for a witneſs againſt you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſayth <hi>Chriſt, He that denyes me before men, him will I deny before my Father;</hi> and thus the practice of the Saints was and is counted Blaſphemy by the profeſſors of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:166821:4"/>Others ſuffer for denying to ſwear at the commands of men, after the cuſtoms of the world, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayth, <hi>Swear not at all, for what is more than Yea and Nay cometh of evil;</hi> and the Apoſtles warneth the Saints above all things <hi>not to ſwear</hi> by any Oath whatſoever, which all that have entered into <hi>Chriſt</hi> have denyed, for he is the Oath and Covenant of God forever.</p>
            <p>Others ſuffer becauſe they are moved of the Lord to go into the Streets and Markets to declare againſt all manner of ſin which abounds there, and to call all to repentance, and to declare the great day of the Lord at hand, and his wrath to be revealed upon ſuch abominable practices: and a ſnare is layd for him that reproveth in the gate, and they ſuffer as diſturbers of the Peace, but what Peace is this which is diſturbed by the crying out againſt ſin? but Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars, Ballad-ſellers, are ſuffered in the ſtreets and markets, and are not counted Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the Peace: Is this the Saints Peace which ſtands in Righteouſneſs, or the Worlds Peace, upholden by man of ſin?</p>
            <p>Others whom the Lord hath called to leave houſes and land, wives and children, fathers and mothers, and hath in love to poor ſouls ſent them out, to declare his love to the world, and the glad tidings of the Goſpel freely, theſe are taken under the name of wanderers and ſtrangers, becauſe they have no earthly poſſeſſions amongſt you; ſome of them by your Law you impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſome you whip out of your Towns, ſome are beaten, ſtoned, and ſhamefully intreated, though they ask you nothing, neither are free to receive any thing from the world, if they would give them, but do wait on their Father for food who ſends them their journey, and thus you entertain ſtrangers, contrary to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all the Saints in all Ages, and the commands of God and the Apoſtles, who warned not to forget to entertain ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, for ſome thereby <hi>have entertained Angels unawares,</hi> but as the men of <hi>Sodom</hi> did compaſs <hi>Lots</hi> houſe, who had entertained ſtrangers, ſo do theſe compaſs the houſes where theſe are, threatning to pull down the houſes and daſh their brains againſt the ſtones in the wall, and this is done when ſuch are with them, who go under the name of Magiſtrates and Miniſters, and the innocent are haled out and ſent to Priſon, though nothing can be charged againſt them but as ſtrangers, who have no habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166821:4"/>
among them. And for ſuch offences as theſe do the poor deſpiſed little ones of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuffer the worſt ſort of Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments that can be invented, in dark holes, under Tyrants, who will not ſuffer their Brethren to viſit them, and all this while all manner of ſin at liberty, and Drunkards, Swearers, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and Whoremongers, and ſuch like men of <hi>Belial,</hi> are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the fitteſt men to be ſet up to witneſs againſt the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and many of thoſe who ſit to judg them are guilty of divers of the foremencioned crimes themſelves; and thus the wicked are ſet up to make the Righteous offenders for a word, who are none in deed, nor can they be convinced of the breach of any juſt Law; and this is not done in ſecret that you know not of. Oh you that bear rule in the Nation, and ought to relieve ſuch, for then might you have an excuſe, but it is done in the Cityes, County, Towns, and Courts, where Juſtice ought to relieve ſuch; and you know this and are ſilent, but it is that you may be left without excuſe, at the great Day of Account, which is near at hand, even the Day of <hi>Sions</hi> recompence, which hath long been troden under foot by the earthly powers! and now will you profeſs your ſelves to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the Scripture your Rule, or ſo much as talk of the practices of the Saints, when ſuch works as theſe are found amongſt you, which were acted by the Heathens, and formal Profeſſors againſt the Saints, but never practiced by the Saints againſt any; neither have you any ground for them in Scripture: O how will you appear before the Almighty, whoſe profeſſions and practiſes are ſo unſutable, and juſtice and mercy is talkt of, but not brought forth.</p>
            <p>Wo, wo, wo unto you, who have not uſed your power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the oppreſſed, do you thus requite the Lord, who hath ſet you free from your Enemyes, and hath ſet you to rule for him over his People! Is this according to your promiſes made to him in the day of your fears, when you were little in your own eys, and now that he hath ſet you free, and you are exalted, ſhall his poor ſimple little ones ſuffer in bondage under you, as under the Tyrants and Biſhops before you, and you not once ſay they are our Brethren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor your hearts pity them! Are you building your Houſes, and ſetting your Neſts on high, and <hi>Sion</hi> lyes waſte, troden upon!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:166821:5"/>Wo is me for you, you high ones, how are you fallen from that tenderneſs I have ſeen in ſome of you, when you were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers with the People of God! but now the ſufferings of the Saints are made a talk at your feaſts to fill your mouths with laughter; and you can eat and drink and riſe up to play, and ſtretch your ſelves upon your Beds of eaſe, but the afflictions of your Brethren are not layd to heart. Wo to you that are at eaſe while the ſimple are enſnared by their Enemyes, God is highly diſpleaſed with you and he will not eſtabliſh you, who have neglected mercy and juſtice. Hearken O ye Prieſts, and give ear O houſe of the King, for judgment is towards you, who have been a ſnare upon <hi>Mispah,</hi> and a net ſpread upon Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> to catch the innocent, you have not been carefull to relieve others when you had power, neither ſhall you deliver your own ſelves at that day: You are ſeeking to be high, but you ſhall finde one above you who is angry with the proud, and will bring down the mighty from their ſeats, that he may relieve the oppreſſed, and let the Priſoners go free, and the Lamb ſhall take the Kingdom. How are you deceived who have ſomtimes been the wiſdom of the Nations; in that you have pulled down others, and ſet your ſelves in the ſame heigh! how is your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment failed you, to think that all this ſhaking and overturning hath no further end but to ſet up fleſh, and to exalt one man to rule over the conſcience of another by his own will, where <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould reign as King for ever! do you here as you would be done by, do you not act contrary to the Scriptures, and practice of all the holy men of God, who durſt never ſit in the Throne of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> perſecute or impriſon any for Conſcience. Oh that you had taken councel at the fear of God, then had you ſtood in your places, and ſhould have known his ſecrets, and that his intent is onely to exalt his Son in Spirit, in the fall of proud fleſh, ſo ſhould you have uſed all your power to make way for his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and you alſo to have caſt down your Crowns at his feet, ſo ſhould you have been eſtabliſhed in his power, a terror to the wicked, removers of oppreſſion, and makers up of the breach, and your names a bleſſing to generations: but now that oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is found with you in as much as the poor deſpiſed little flock of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſuffered under you, as under thoſe whom the Lord
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166821:5"/>
removed before, when it hath been in your hands to relieve them, and you have not done it, and you that have ſo much cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in words, and yet have been bold to limit him in his Kingdom, (the Conſciences of his Saints) therefore above all the reſt you ſhall not eſcape unpuniſhed, for the Lord looked that you who have ſeen his love and pity to you, in ſetting you above your Enemyes and Fears, ſhould now have had pity on your Brethren, and walked humbly before him; and for that end he put power into your hands, and removed thoſe that were before you, and left none to oppoſe you, that you might freely act in mercy and judgment and righteouſneſs, but ſeeing you have forgotten the Lord and his work which to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ward was good, and are become exceeding high, and cruel as others, and the poor are not delivered by you from the hand of the oppreſſor and him that is too ſtrong for him, neither have you chearfully gone on in unity, in the work of the Lord and his will but ſtand up in your own wills, oppoſing the deliverance of the righteous ſeed. Therefore now will I ariſe, ſayth the Lord, who have long holden my peace, for I am full of jealouſie for <hi>Sion</hi> who is troden upon, and I will appear for her in the midſt of her Enemyes, and I will gather the outcaſts thereof, who have not been regarded, but have been ſcattered by you, as the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world, and as you have ſcattered and not pityed, ſo ſhall you be ſcattered, and none ſhall pity you; for the worlds outcaſts are my jewels, and I will bring them to poſſeſs the gates of their Enemyes: Even by the word of the Almighty ſhall this be accompliſhed, the Day is near at hand.</p>
            <p>Wherefore awake all you to whom oppreſſion is a burden, whom the proud have troden upon, and you have been as people without hope, neither have known any way to look for help, for every man hath become vain: Now ariſe up out of all your earthly expectations, and ſtand up to meet the Lord our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, who is riſen to deliver his people, the promiſed ſeed who is in Covenant with him, and to gather them from among the heathen and them that have made prey upon them, becauſe they have not known him who will ſave them. And now look no more to the Arm of Fleſh for Freedom, for therein hath been
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166821:6"/>
your wo, but wayt for the Deliverer out of <hi>Sion,</hi> the Ancient of Days, and God of <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſeed, who hath letten you ſee the emptyneſs of all created helps to which your eys have been looking that you might return, and complain to him onely, who is the Fountain from whom all his finde pity.</p>
            <p>And now a word to the wiſe amongſt you, for as much as the Lord hath ſhewed me that there is a Seed amongſt you, whoſe hearts are not wholly hardened, nor have wilfully ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ears againſt the Cry of the oppreſſed, nor have been conſenting to the cruelty that hath been acted and is intended againſt the innocent; to you I ſay ariſe and deliver your ſelves from the guilt of Oppreſſion, and Cruelty of theſe men, and humble your ſelves before the Lord, that you may receive wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from him, and boldneſs to declare againſt all violence and injuſtice, and ſet your ſelves to deliver the oppreſſed to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, that you may be hid, and have a ſure house, and be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: take heed that you walk not by example of others, but in the light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> which guides the conſcience, and that will keep you tender-hearted in bowels of mercy to all, and let it not ſeem ſtrange to you to ſee others wholly ſet on miſchief, but conſider, could ever any of your cruel oppreſſors believe, though God hath always ſent to warn them before the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment come, that thereby he might leave them without excuſe, and be clear when he comes to take vengeance, but they have hardened themſelves againſt all reproof: and marvel not to ſee it ſo at this day, for the ſeed of the proud is but one in all ages. Wherefore minde the fear of God and his Law, and conſent not to any thing becauſe of a multitude, but for Righteouſneſs and Equityes ſake; and having Righteouſneſs before you fear not the face of any, nor the reproach of men, but be valiant for the truth, the glory of God, and freedom of every oppreſſed one, and victory is before you, if you be faithfull; and the Lord God Almighty bleſs, proſper, and guide all the faithfull among you, to keep clear out of all the conſultations of the wicked, that you may never conſent to any thing but what is of God, warranted in Scriptures, and practiced by the Saints, that you may no longer reſt in a Profeſſion of what the Saints were,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166821:6"/>
and act to the contrary but that you may come to be guided in all things by the ſame Spirit, kept out of all the wiſdom of the world, and the fear of God be amongſt you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written by the movings of the Lord in one that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes the Ruines of the Nacion; for want of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Iuſtice, and Mercy, whom the World calls
Iames Nayler.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Westmerland,</hi> 
                  <date>the 9th Moneth 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="warning">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:166821:7"/>
            <head>A Warning to the Rulers of <hi>ENGLAND. Not to uſurp Dominion over the Conſcience, nor to give forth Laws contrary to that in the Conſcience.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Law it was added becauſe of tranſgreſſion, it came not by the will of man, but was revealed to <hi>Moſes</hi> of God, and is perfect according to that in the conſcience, it was added becauſe of tranſgreſſors, who walk contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to that in the conſcience, which is pure of God, there is the ſeat of blaſphemy, he ſpeaks what he is not, and what he doth not, and ſpeaks evil of thoſe things he knows not, and he that acts contrary to that in the conſcience acts contrary to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Law of God, and there he lives in the luſt, when the Law ſayth thou ſhalt not luſt; he that luſteth goeth forth, he ſteals, he covets his neighbours wife, and his neighbours goods, he kills and doth murder, and he goes forth and breaks the Sabboth, and he that breaks one breaks all; and heer the righteous Law takes hold upon him, that is perfect, and ſlays him.</p>
            <p>But he that dwels in that which is pure, exerciſing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God and man, the Law takes not hold upon him, it was not made for ſuch the righteous, but for the ſinners: and who are without the fear of the Lord caſts this Law behinde their backs, and who reſpects perſons, and his minde that luſteth and goeth forth from the pure in this conſcience, there the ſpirit is erred into the earth and for the earth, as <hi>Balaams</hi> was, then that minde ſpeaks evil of the truth.</p>
            <p>And this Law is made already, which is the Law of God, &amp; need not be made again; but all are to wait to receive it, which is perfect and is a ground againſt all unrighteouſneſs and Sinners: where it is received it is underſtood, what it takes hold upon, which was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſors, not for the Righteous, but it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the Righteous, and gives way for the Truth, it meddles not with the Righteous as laying any thing upon them, for it doth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166821:7"/>
not reſpect any mans Perſon, it takes hold upon all who act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that in the Conſcience: it doth not meddle with that in the Conſcience which is pure, which is perfect, that is its own, and that ſaith <hi>the Law is holy, juſt, and good,</hi> in its place, but it is for them which are without, and it doth not ſpeak evill of the Magiſtrates which are in this Law and have received it which is perfect, but of the Evil the Law judgeth, which is perfect, but it exalts juſtice, and dominion; Dominion which is according to the Soul, and that in the Conſcience, it is for the keeping them who act contrary to that in the Conſcience in order, a limit to the Luſt, for it ſayth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Luſt,</hi> (for who act contrary to that in the Conſcience run out of Order) that there ſhall be none that abuſe themſelves with mankinde, no Fighter, and how full is the Land of them! nor no reſpecters of Perſons, and all who acts according to this in the Conſcience: that in the Conſcience is but one, in it there is no damnable Hereſie, nor no Blaſphemy, nor no licencious practiſes, for they ariſe out of that nature that acts contrary to that in the Conſcience, without the fear of the Lord, and that ſpeaks evill of Magiſtrates and Magiſtracy, and deſtroyes the Common-wealth, for this in the Conſcience guids into the fear of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now you not having received this perfect Law, but makeing Lawes in your wils and mindes contrary to this in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and above this in the Conſcience; who acts according to that in the Conſcience cannot ſubmit to them, for thoſe Lawes are changable, but this is for ever, which was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſors, and takes hold upon the Sinners and Tranſgreſſors outward, to the hewing down of ſuch.</p>
            <p>But you that go to make Lawes in your wils againſt the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and meddle with the Righteous, and them that act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in the Conſcience, which is according to the Law, of God, which is perfect, and for ever, the Law of God will hew you all down, which is for ever, as it has done many generacions before you: and the righteous Seed ſuffered in all generacions by ſuch Lawes, therefore to that in your Conſciences I ſpeak to wait upon the Lord, that you may receive the Law of God, which is pure, which is juſt, which is perfect according to that in the Conſcience, for there is Woes and Plauges gone out againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166821:8"/>
this Nacion, leſt you be ſwept away with the ſeed of evill doers and in the way as your Fathers who have tranſgreſſed the pure Law, and that in the Conſcience, and ſtroven with the Law which is in the will, to keep down that in the Conſcience; for there<note place="margin">At the ſecond Seſſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irſt year of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> has been a Law &amp; an Act made, which Act did the Martyrs ſuffer by in <hi>Queen Maryes</hi> dayes, who was the maintainer of Popery: this has the Engliſh Miniſtry who profeſs the Miniſtry of <hi>Chriſt</hi> got to limit the Spirit of the Lord, to keep them in their Pulpits and it has been their Guard; and they cry againſt Popery, and themſelves maintain the Popiſh Law, to priſon and to perſecute them that have the Life of the Scriptures made manifeſt in them.</p>
            <p>Oh never profeſs Chriſt, and guard your Church and Miniſtry as you call it, with a Popiſh Antichriſtian Law, let this never be mencioned in Ages to come as it is mencioned in this Age, how many have ſuffred by her Law, and ſuffers now, and yet you cry up the Goſpel, and cry againſt ſuch as act according to that in the Conſcience; but this is a ſhame to thoſe who have received the Goſpel of Chriſt, and walk in the Spirit that gave forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and have the pure Law of God, whereby many have been impriſoned, and are Priſoned.</p>
            <p>Now conſider and ſee your ſelves, if you have not made and maintained this Act againſt the Scripture, when the Scripture ſayth, <hi>If any thing be revealed to another that ſits by, let the firſt hold his Peace, for yee may all ſpeak one by one,</hi> and the Teachers of the World, put up Peticions to you, againſt them who have been moved of the Lord to ſpeak his word; ſo here Teachers and you who be in Authority you both act againſt Scripture, your Law it is againſt the Scripture, and their Teaching is againſt the Scripture, and ſo its juſt with God to hew you all down toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the Miniſter of God ſayd, <hi>You may all Propheſy one by one: if any thing be revealed to him that ſits by, let the firſt hold his Peace:</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> gave that Liberty, who had received the Law from God: and that was in all the Churches of the Saints, that they might ſpeak one by one,</p>
            <p>Now here you that make a Law contrary to that in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and you that put up Peticions for a Law, have cleared your ſelves, both makers of the Law, and ſeekers for the Law,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166821:8"/>
not to have the Spirit of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and his Lawes which are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and not to have the Spirit of the Miniſter of God, of <hi>Paul,</hi> who gave that Freedom, that all may ſpeak one by one, and here yee do limit the <hi>Holy One</hi> and the Spirit of the Lord God; and ſo ty People up in Forms and Sects, and bring up damnable He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and Blaſphemies, who bring People contrary to that in the Conſcience, for that is but one in ten-thouſand, and is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law of God, which is perfect, and the Law of God takes not hold upon that, (A warning to you all, and be warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and fear God)</p>
            <p>Now in the Church of God, where they ſpoke one by one, there was no diſorder nor diſtraction, where all were guided by one Spirit; the Law has nothing to do with the Church of God <hi>that is the Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> and they are in Peace and Unity, and the Law was never made for ſuch, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Head of the <hi>Church,</hi> the Head of the Body, who is the end of the Law, and therefore ſilence all Fleſh (who would make a Law upon <hi>Chriſt</hi>) from making Lawes for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Law of God takes hold upon ſuch who are Murtherers, who act unrighteouſneſs, them that abuſe themſelves with Mankinde, them that are without, and act without, and you that meddle with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that in the Conſcience; the Law you have not received from God, but the Plauges will be pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon you: The Law of God is contrary to that in your Wils, according to that in the Conſcience, and they are both perfect, and it is not known but as it is revealed, and the miniſter of God is perfect, according to that in the Conſcience, and it owns the perfect Law, for the Miniſter of God is to bring from under all Sin, and the ocaſion of all Lawes, and this we witneſs, yea Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands! Praiſed be the Lord for ever.</p>
            <p>They that fear the Lord they have mutuall Peace among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, you need not make a Law for them; for the Law is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that are without the fear of God, and there is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance, and ſuch the Law takes hold upon,</p>
            <p>And as touching preventing the abuſing and evil ſpeaking of Magiſtrates, there need not be a Law upon them that fear the Lord, for they are taught by the Spirit of the Lord, that in the Conſcience, to fear the Lord and own the perfect Law which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166821:9"/>
is holy, juſt, and good in its place; and own juſtice and the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Dominion; but as it was in the time of <hi>Iude,</hi> ſuch Teachers as went in the way of <hi>Cain</hi> to envy and after the error of <hi>Balaam,</hi> who periſh in the gainſaying of <hi>Core,</hi> what they ſpoke they knew naturally, and in thoſe things they corrupted themſelves, as <hi>England</hi> has many of ſuch who have told us that <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> has been the Original, and the Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe has been the Church and the Temple, and ſprinkling In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants has been the Baptiſm, and the Letter has been the Light, and the Letter has been the Word, and thoſe are the Teachers that were made Miniſters at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridg,</hi> by the will of man; but we finde theſe things all natural, and the natural man knows not the things of God, but they are known natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and keeps People natural, and knowing theſe things are contrary to the Scripture, therefore do we trample upon them, and deny them; and the Magiſtrat having his Law changeable, (not receiving the Law from God which is perfect and endures for ever) and not according to that in the conſcience, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture, but would limit the Spirit of the Lord, we deny them &amp; that which is contrary to the ſoul, and contrary to that in the conſcience, but that which is according to the ſoul and that in the conſcience we own and honour in our ſouls, for that is perfect and endures for ever, and does not ſpeak evil of Dignity nor of Dominion, and to that the ſoul muſt be ſubject: but as touching the Miniſtry which I ſayd we trampled upon, which is natural, we having received the ſame ſpirit according to the meaſure that gave forth the Scripture, by which we are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into one Body, ſo with that we deny their ſprinkling of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, which they call Baptiſm, becauſe there is no example for it in the Scripture; and that ſpirit that gave forth the Scripture ſayd, the Church is in God, and therefore we deny the Church of the world which is natural, and they that were made Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were made by the will of God and not by the will of man, and ſo do we; and the Letter ſayth <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Light, and they that ſay the Letter is the Light would diſthrone <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and they that ſay the Letter is the Word ſets it up before God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes God, for the Letter ſayth God is the Word, and they that ſay the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> are the Original, they who were the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166821:9"/>
Miniſters of the Word, which was in the beginng, before many Languages were, ſpoke the Word among the <hi>Hebrews</hi> and were perſecuted; now if the <hi>Hebrew</hi> had been the Original they would have received them; and the Apoſtle he ſpoke among the <hi>Greeks</hi> and they counted the Croſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi> a fooliſh thing: now had that been the Original <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> they would have embraced it: the Eternal Word which was in the beginning before all Languages were, breaks in pieces all Languages and tramples upon them, and brings all into one Language, for that which keeps in many Languages keeps in confuſion, and always learning, therefore with the Word which ever was, which is made manifeſt, which gathers our hearts together to God, we deny their Original; for the Apoſtle he denyed all his Learning when he came to know the Word which was and is the Original which endures for ever. And as touching giving fitting liberty for them that fear the Lord, for that you have no ground in the Scripture, for if you go to meddle with them that fear the Lord with your Law, you buſie your ſelves with thoſe things that you have nothing to do withall; to that in your conſciences I ſpeak, for you have nothing to do to meddle with them that act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that in the conſcience, and act in righteouſneſs; and as giving liberty for ſuch, you are them that would limit the holy One, and ty up and priſon that in the conſcience; he that meddles with that in the conſcience goes about to ſearch the heart, and where it acts forth you will have a Law to act upon it, when it acts contrary to your wils for that in the conſcience is perfect, is pure, it teſtifies againſt all opinions, and all Sects, and all Hereſie, and all Blaſphemy, and all falſe Miniſtry, and all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ways, for they all ariſe out of that nature which acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that in the conſcience, and that in the conſcience is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God, and he that makes a Law upon that makes a Law againſt God, and he that is guided by this in the conſcience to walk towards God and man, the fleſh is not defiled; he ſpeaks not evil of Dignity; and there is no man with his will has any thing to do to reſtrain or give liberty for this; and where have you an example for this in all the Scripture, or <hi>Moſes</hi> who was a Miniſter of the Law, who had received it from God, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained any mans conſcience, and he wiſhed that all the Lords
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166821:10"/>
people were Prophets; and the Miniſter of God ſayd, <hi>Ye may all ſpeak one by one;</hi> and ye need not care for an Act or Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as touching them, and for ſhame let it never be mentioned that there ſhould be a Law for them that fear God as if there were diſturbance among them, or as if they were not in a mutual peace; but theſe are ſuch Teachers that deſire ſuch things that have the likeneſs of a Church, the likeneſs of a Baptiſm, the likeneſs of a Miniſtry, and the likeneſs of a Communion, and when any has been moved of the Lord to go ſpeak againſt them, they have openly ſhewed themſelves to be quite without the fear of the Lord, and ſtrangers to the life that gave forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Prieſts, Magiſtrats, and People; for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayd, he would that all the Lords people <hi>were Prophets;</hi> and the Apoſtle ſayd, <hi>Ye may all propheſie one by one;</hi> and when theſe things have been practiſed according to the Scripture, they who have been moved by the Spirit that is unlimited, to ſpeak the Word of the Lord as it was revealed, this the Magiſtrat he hath limited with his Law and ſent them to Priſon; heer the Law is againſt Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and that Spirit that gave it forth: I charge you in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and againſt the Miniſters of God that had the Law of God, and ſayd, <hi>Ye may all propheſie;</hi> and heer you Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that deſire this Law are againſt Scriptures and the Apoſtles, and clear your ſelves from having the Spirit, and your Churches to be no Churches; for when the Word of the Lord is ſpoken, ſome fall a ſtriking, ſome a punching, beating, haling, throwing down, and lays for dead, and the Law of God is perfect, and gives freedom to ſpeak what is revealed from God, and it hears with patience, and the Miniſter of God gives freedom to ſpeak what is revealed.</p>
            <p>And you that ſay you will make Laws according to the patern of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for you to go act according to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law word by word, and to take up the Form and not have it revealed to you, as it was to him, you are to be denyed, as having the Form with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the power, and to be turned away from; Oh therefore fear the Lord God and minde that in the conſcience, which is pure, which will teach you the fear of the Lord, and bring you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Law from God, and the power, then you may give it forth to others, but not till then; would you have a Law now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166821:10"/>
made contrary to your wils upon you, the Law of God is upon you, and will be for ever, who acts contrary to that in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the Law of God is to keep perfect, it takes hold upon that which acts contrary to that which is perfect, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God is to preſent every one perfect, and to bring from under the occaſion of all Laws.</p>
            <p>A word from the Lord. Friends, take heed of making any Law contrary to that in the conſcience, for if you do, it will be againſt God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God will hew down it and you with his Sword, for it is drawn out of the ſheath and furbiſhed, and fit to ſlay Noblemen and great men, Captains beware, be low, minde that in your conſciences which is of God, to guide your mindes up to God; fear and beware of the Sword, for its drawn out againſt you, leſt it come upon you, and wait in that which is pure in your conſciences to riſe and guide your mindes to God, and cry for juſtice, and walk in it, for whatſoever is not juſt and juſtice, muſt be hewen down, that juſtice may ſtand up, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that in the conſcience which is pure of God, for now God alone will be exalted, and that which is exalted muſt be thrown down and all the loftineſs of men ſhall be layd low, and the haughtyneſs of men ſhall be brought down, and the glory of man, and his honor and renoun ſhall be layd in the duſt, and the glory of the Lord ſhall ariſe, and his Majeſty, to ſhake terribly the earth, and the Idols of Gold and Silver ſhall be caſt away, as the carnal part is deſtroyed, all your Idols will ceaſe, and the pure God be exalted and loved.</p>
            <p>Oh Friends, make not Laws in your own wils for they that did, ever ſlew the juſt, and had a Priſon for <hi>Christ,</hi> where he was made manifeſt, and the Prophets and Apoſtles ſuffered by their Laws who were made in their wils, for witneſſing forth a good conſcience many ſuffered death, for they ſayd they had a Law, if any one ſayd he was the Son of God, he might die, and ſo the Law in the wil doth perſecute the Son of God now where he is made manifeſt, as the North part of this Nation doth witneſs, who has fulfilled that Law in perſecuting and impriſoning the Son of God where he is made manifeſt. And <hi>Paul</hi> when hee was brought from the Temple outward, and the Prieſts outwardly, for that Seperacion and witneſſing a good Conſcience towards
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166821:11"/>
God and man, he ſuffered, ſo their Lawes being in their Wils, took hold upon him for acting from a pure Conſcience, ſo it doth now upon the ſame: O therefore wait upon the Lord for direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that your Lawes may be according to that in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and againſt that which is contrary to a pure Conſcience; as the Law of God was added not for the Righteous, but for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: the juſt Law takes hold upon them, and this Law is not according to the Will of man, neither is <hi>Chriſt</hi> according to the will of man, who fulfils this Law in man, and takes away the ground and the occaſion of the Law, which the Law is upon, therefore minde that which is contrary to your Wils, to receive the Law of God, which is contrary to mans will, which is perfect and received from God, and hath power over a man as long as he lives.</p>
            <p>Written from the Spirit of the Lord; a friend to your ſoules and your eternall good, and the eſtabliſhing of Righteouſneſſe, and the pefect Law of God, to the intent of cleanſing the Land of Evell-doers, and the Tranſgreſſors of the perfect Law of God: And who knows this, are come out of <hi>Egypt, Pharaoh</hi> nor none of his Hoaſt knoweth it, nor the Egyptians, but who are brought out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> So God Almighty bleſſe &amp; direct you all, who have a fear and thirſt towards him, for this is the Day of your viſitacion, while you have time prize it,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Fox.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Weſtmerland</hi> 
                  <date>the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of the month called November. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>Theſe Papers were prepared and intended to have been delivered to every member of Parliament, but before they could be got out the Parliament diſſolved.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
